Hello everyone and welcome to this
session about what's new in agentic
development for the 20126 release wave
2. I'm Kberis and I'm presenting
together with Artur Wensel.
Today's agenda. First we are going to
talk about the agentic developer loop.
Then about the snapshot debugging MCP.
Then Arur will perform a presentation of
the snapshot debugging MCP.
Then I will talk about the AI language
server protocol the sampling profiling
MCP and then I will finish with a demo
of the sampling profiling MCP. This is
the big picture from 10,000 ft. The
developer starts with a prompt because
there is a real problem to solve. Maybe
the production environment is slow or
maybe user found a bug that was not seen
during development and testing.
The prompt describes the problem. The
agent then plans the investigation and
calls the right standard protocols.
Let's see the architecture behind the
process.
ALSP grounds the agent in the source
code by providing exact definition
references and type information.
AL tool acts as the local proxy. It
handles standard input and output
communication, authentication,
business center routing and delivery of
the captured artifacts.
The business central MCP server provides
the runtime tools and resources for
snapshot debugging and sampling
profiling.
Together,
these interfaces produce grounded
evidence, capture call stacks and
variables and sample AICPU profile data.
This is the agentic developer loop.
understand the source, collect evidence
from the real environment, and use that
evidence to explain and fix the problem.
Snapshot debugging. We already know
snapshot debugging as a tool available
to developers in Visual Studio Code. The
agentic workflow follows the same
principles, but the agent can now
coordinate the investigation.
A typical scenario is that you have a
bug in a production environment. Let's
say a web client.
You configure the snapshot debugging MCP
server for the business central
environment.
Ask the agent to capture the next
matching web client session.
Reproduce the AL exception.
Tell the agent that the reproduction is
complete. and then let the agent collect
the snapshot and analyze the capture
call stacks and variables.
If the first snapshot does not contain
enough information, the agent can use
the als to find the exact callers of the
failing function and place snap points
at better locations.
The agent can then arm another capture
for the known session ID or the next
matching web client session. And this
loop can be repeated until the reason
for failure is found.
So how we set up snapshot debugging? The
snapshot debugging MCP server is built
into the standard Microsoft business
central MCP infrastructure.
There are three ways to connect.
Our AL tool Swiss Army knife can act as
a proxy. It is an MCP host for the
business central MCP server and an MCP
server for your local client.
Visual Studio Code can configure the
same business center target in the
launch.json
extension registers and starts the
snapshot MCP proxy and then can reuse
the existing AI development signin.
The third option is to create your own
MCP host that accesses the Microsoft
Business Center MCP servers
troubleshooting infrastructure.
Arthur will now demonstrate how the
snapshot debugging MCP server works.
>> Um thank you Coleman. So uh my demo
going to be exactly what you said that
user is uh working in business central
and uh performing the very standard um
procedure is trying to post the purchase
invoice um and face the error which is
not clear for the user. It says advanced
checked failed and apparently what user
can do it uh can just copy that error
message and send to engineer to um to
debug and then figure out what is wrong.
But now with the great capabilities that
you presented, uh here is what we can
do. Let me just open first Visual Studio
Code to show you the very small sample
of the code. So this is the PT that I
installed. I um subscribe to the event
for the posting and then in that um
subscriber uh I verify if any of those
three fields are blank. Uh and in this
case I throw an error. Um [snorts] very
simple for this demo. I have uh my MCPJ
JSON with um snapshot debugging. I have
LSP everything is ready um in this
setup. So how do I how do we debug? How
do I understand what is the problem
there? I can actually use the snapshot
debugging and the user session for this.
Let me switch to GitHub copilot CLI. I
have a long prompt and I will explain to
you um the important part of it. So the
first one I say that the user reports
the advanced check failed problem. So I
explicitly tell the agent the exact
error message. Why it is important?
Because the agent should find it and I
say when posting the purchase invoice
then I instruct the agent to initialize
the snapshot debugging in the next
session. This is the important part
because by the time user tell me that
there is an error they might log off.
There's no current session. I cannot
attach to the session. So there's going
to be some next session probably the
other day. So I instruct the agent agent
to attach to the next session. Then I
say find the place in the code where
this error throws and set the snap
points to troubleshoot this. So I rely
on the agent to go through the code and
then set those snap points individ
individual uh places in the code and
they collect all the variables around
this one and uh we know that the agent
they are smart enough with the LSP to to
do that. Um and then when I want to say
because I don't know when when the user
going to log in to the to the session.
So what I want to do I want to combine
the scenario with telemetry. I want to
instruct agent to start pulling the
telemetry every 15 seconds. Again for
the sake of the demo in the real world
it's going to be uh hours. Um and I want
to start pulling for the exact error in
telemetry. And once it found agent found
it it will stop pulling download the
snapshot and investigate the root cause.
So this is all the explanation for that
prompt. Let's see how it works in
practice.
So I'm going to run it and uh a couple
of things going to happen. I will
explain all of them one by one. So first
I mention telemetry. There's a certain
scale that uh captured to understand how
to work with telemetry. Then uh agent
going to start looking for the exact
error uh in the in the code unit to
identify how to set the snap points. So
we run the search.
So let's see how that's going. And then
there's a tool that is called initialize
snapshot debugging. So it is called in
the next session with all the snap
points that the agent currently
collected.
Um so it is identified the agent was
able to figure out where is the error
message comes from. This is great. Uh
and then it should start polling for
this specific um error message. So let's
see how it works.
Yes, it says scheduling every 15
seconds. That's great. Snapshot
debugging is armed for the next web
client session. Great. I think we are
we're all set. The agent was able to
identify everything. And you see uh we
already have the schedule prompt
executed. There is a long prompt that
agent automatically generated or what
exactly needs to happen. It loads the
scale. It goes to telemetry and you see
no matching telemetry evident event.
What's going to happen next? Now I'm
switching my hat. Now I'm a user again.
Uh the next day I log into that session.
Uh and I went and log in. I see the the
same thing like we had with a snapshot
debugging. I see that the snapshot
debugging is turned on for my session.
That's great. Uh and me as a user
understand that uh probably engineer
going to help me with that. So I do the
very same thing. I want to post the
document to see the same error and
that's great. And when it's happened and
let me go back to GitHub compile CLI. So
the next um schedule prompt is running
um and then it should be able to
retrieve from telemetry the exact event.
Uh it takes the call stack the exact
error and now we can see that the uh
error is appeared. it stopped the
snapshot debugging and now it's trying
to download uh the snapshot and
investigate um the call stack and the
values of of all the variables and it
will try to reason over that snapshot
and um uh and uh give me the uh
understanding of what is happening. So
let's give it just a second to download
the snapshot and uh reason over it.
it will um take some time to reading all
the snapshots and then collecting all
the values and comparing u to the code
that I have in the code unit and finally
I have a root cause found um agent was
able to identify that one of those three
fields was actually filled in by the
user but two other fields were not. So
now me as an engineer I can get back to
the user and then tell what exactly um
is going wrong and uh help them to move
forward to fill in those fields and uh
successfully post the document. Back to
you common.
>> Thank you Arthur. Let's continue.
Let's talk about the AI language server
protocol. The language server protocol
is an industry standard that connects
development environments
to language specific intelligence.
It is also how the AL extension provides
AL language features in Visual Studio
Code.
The same protocol is now available to
agents. Instead of relying only on text
search, an agent can resolve exact
definition, references, types, symbols,
implementations, and callers.
The semantic grounding is valuable
throughout the developer loop for our
troubleshooting scenarios. It helps the
agent place correct snap points, follow
a capture stack frame into the source
and understand the functions identified
by a performance profile. Let's continue
with the sampling profiling MCP. The
story here is very similar to the
snapshot debugging MCP server. Sampling
profiling is exposed through the
business central MCP server. The MCP
host that we provide is again a tool.
There is however one important
difference from snapshot debugging.
To start a profiling schedule, the agent
needs the numeric business central
session ID that it should target.
Let me show you two ways to obtain the
session ID. For a web client session,
the user can find it on the help and
support page and provide it directly
or the session ID can be inferred. As an
example, the agent can use telemetry to
identify the relevant session from the
workload and environment.
Once the session ID is known, the agent
starts a limited sampling schedule.
Business center watches the matching
activities and returns AI CPU profile
files. It also returns an overview of
activity duration, CQL calls, HTTP calls
and only for the MCP server memory
information.
The permissions are again checked by
Business Central for the signin user.
They are the same permission as for the
manual workflow. To profile your own
session, you need permission to create
profile schedules and read the resulting
performance profile. To profile another
user session, you need the D365
attach debug permission set.
So let's do some demos.
We have seen how an agent can
investigate a failure from captured
runtime state. Now let's ask a different
question. What if nothing fails but
business center is simply slow? Let me
first show you how I set up the MCP
server.
It is very similar to the information
available in a launch.json file. You
need to specify the environment, the
environment type. These are things you
know from the launch.json, JSON aren't
they the extra parameter in the option
to save
the CPU profile files locally for
further analysis. Now assume that I have
a schedule task that makes business
center very slow. Here is a small demo
app that creates this slow workload. It
hammers SQL server with an abnormally
high number of SQL statements as a batch
schedule task would do. So let's start.
Now I'm going to use copilot cle to
start sampling this session. The prompt
that I'm going to use is the following.
Business center is slow on session one.
Profile it please until I say done and
tell me why.
So what will happen here is uh that uh
we are going to connect to the business
central MCP server and the sampling
profiling session is going to be
started. While this is going on I'm
going to do the second demo. I'm not
going to do it live because it takes
five minutes but we are going to go
through it because it's a very
interesting demo. So let's start that
one.
Here I have a special agent that I ask
to look for special telemetry tags.
If a tag measures if a tag that measures
slow CQL calls a hit, it should find the
associated NSD session ID. With that
session ID, the agent will instruct
itself to analyze why is it slow. From
there, it will hook into the sampling
debugging MCP server, get her samples,
and create a verdict. So this was my
original prompt. The BCL background
workload is slow. Find the correct NSD
session capture. Capture one complete
workload pass and tell me why. Do a full
analysis at the end emphasizing the slow
sequels and their associated AI code. So
I will scroll through the result and you
can see how detailed it is. In the first
part, it described what it did and what
logic it used to start sampling. So it
was you looking for this tag. When it
found this tag, it found this session.
When it found this session, it initiated
a sampling uh session. It waited until
it found three complete activities. And
when it that when it finished with that
one, it came with a verdict.
And well, let's see what is in the
verdict. The verdict says that it has
used CQL
for 58% and it sampled AI files for 40%.
It used 30,000 CQL statements in 5
seconds.
It actually shows which statements it
has used and it bound to the methods
that were causing it.
More importantly, it actually says
another issue that there was an issue
with the index because we were indexing
by category code.
So as you can see this is a very very
detailed uh analysis. So let's go back
to the original
problem and say that we are done here.
You know we actually have done the same
thing should happen here. There was a
distinction between these two scenarios.
I called the left hand side a user
scenario because I was using a session
ID and I called the second one a full
agentic scenario because here an agent
was doing everything by itself.
As you can see the schedule will be
stopped and we should get to the same
result. Just going back to the second
scenario
the agent provides root causes and
fixes. It actually told us what was the
problem and what we should do to prevent
these things happening again.
The first demo is still running. As you
can see, it's using the language server
right now to understand the source code
and come to probably same result as the
agent was coming to.
Let's wait a little bit more until it
finishes.
Yep. Task complete. Root cause NSD
session was repeatedly running
background code unit and it reached
exactly the same conclusion that it
found 30,000 rows. Now here we have a
brief overview of what happened. But you
know that depends on the prompt. Had I
been prompted I want a detailed result I
would have got something similar like
here.
This finishes our two demos. The key
takeaway is that these are not isolated
tools. ALSP snapshot debugging and the
sampling profiling MCP should the
business central MCP server work
together as one agenting developer loop.
Understand, capture, measure, and fix.
Thank you.
>> Thank you.